Guide to the Maria Edgeworth Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Maria Edgeworth collection
1791-1940
GEN MSS 330
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.1
(6 boxes)
Collection includes Bertha Coolidge Slade's collection of Edgeworth materials, including correspondence between Edgeworth and Richard Bentley and others; copies of letters by Edgeworth, including correspondence with Rachel Mordacai Lazarus and John Murray; letters by Richard Lovell Edgeworth; holograph poem entitled "Enigma"; drawing of Edgeworth's Library by F. W. Fairholt; and Slade's research files, gathered during research for her book, "Maria Edgeworth, 1767-1849, a Bibliographical Tribute," which consist of correspondence with rare book and manuscript dealers including Michael Sadleir, and notes about various editions of Edgeworth's writings. Also included is original Edgeworth material from other sources, including correspondence with Anna Letitia Barbauld and others; letters by Richard Lovell Edgeworth; several engravings of Edgeworth; and an undated corrected typescript by E. G. Ewens entitled "Maria Edgeworth: A Study."
Edgeworth, Maria, 1768-1849
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded in series level notes. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Maria Edgeworth, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to February 1998 have been organized into two series. Series I, Bertha Coolidge Slade Gift, consists of original correspondence and documents by Edgeworth and others, and copies of Edgeworth correspondence; Mrs. Slade's research files on books and articles by Maria and Richard Lovell Edgeworth, including descriptions of various editions; correspondence between Mrs. Slade and various rare book and manuscript dealers, including notes, invoices and descriptions of Edgeworth material; and correspondence between Mrs. Slade and various other people, primarily concerning her Edgeworth collection. Series II, Materials from Other Sources, consists of original Edgeworth material acquired from various other sources.
Barbauld, Mrs. (Anna Letitia), 1743-1825; Bentley, Richard, 1794-1871; Coolidge, Bertha; Edgeworth, Maria, 1768-1849; Edgeworth, Richard Lovell, 1744-1817; Ewens, E. G.; Fairholt, F. W. (Frederick William), 1814-1866; Lazarus, Rachel Mordecai, 1788-1838; Murray, John; Sadleir, Michael, 1888-1957
- Bertha Coolidge Slade Gift, 1791-1940, n.d.; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of Bertha Coolidge Slade, 1939-1951
  - CORRESPONDENCE OF MARIA EDGEWORTH
    Includes letters from Richard Lovell Edgeworth
    - 4 ALS and parts of two letters to Richard Bentley, 1837-48, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 2 ALS to Mr. Curtis, Edgeworthstown, 1844, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ALS to Lady Darnley, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS from Richard Lovell Edgeworth to Mrs. Esther Day, Bristol, 1791 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Autograph envelope, addressed to William Gibbons of Richmond, Surrey, [Edgeworthstown], 1840 Aug 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      1 envelope in a paper-case containing explanatory remarks
    - ALS to R. Hunter, [Edgeworthstown?], [n.y.] Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes: typescript copy of the letter
    - Letters to Mrs. Inchbald, 1814, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes: Manuscript copies of of letters [by BCS?], one original ALS dated 1817 May 17
      Letter dated 1817 May 21 by RLE, letter dated 1814 unsigned
    - Typescript copies of correspondence between Rachel Mordacai Lazarus and Maria Edgeworth, 1815-38, Warrenton, North Carolina; Edgeworthstown, Ireland (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
      3 ALS from Mrs. Lazarus and 11 replies from Miss Edgeworth and her father including notes about the letters
    - Typescript copies of letters from J. G. Lockhart 1827-29, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 28 ALS to Mrs. Miles, [v.p.], 1811-18 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
      4 ALS undated. The postscript to ALS for Feb 27 [n.y.] has sample of silk attached. Accompanied by 1 sheet of instructions for purchasing dress material, etc., with samples tipped in
    - ALS to Miles, Johnson & Co., [London], [1813 May 28] (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Manuscript and typescript copies of letters to John Murray, 1833-43 (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
    - Letter, written in the third person, by an unknown hand, to John Murray, Edgeworthstown, 1817 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - ALS to "My dear Countess", 1841 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Regarding the placing of the daughter of "poor Mrs. Hewitt, widow of the Captain of the FAIRY in an asylum," and mentioning the illness of her aunt, Mary Sneyd
    - 2 ALS to Louisa Norton, 1835, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Letter of 1835 discusses American and English proverbs and encloses an engraving designed by Frances Anna (Beaufort) Edgeworth to illustrate Miss Edgeworth's The Bracelets, published in her Parent's Assistant. Letter of 1837 mentions her Harry and Lucy and The Dame School Holiday; published in BCS's Maria Edgeworth, 1767-1849, A Bibliograph- ical Tribute, London [1937], p. 4
    - AL in the third person to Mr. O'Flannagan, Edgeworthstown, 1840 May 29? (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Includes: typescript copy of letter
    - 4 ALS to Madame de Pastoret, 18[03]-18 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Letters of 1803 and 1814 include letters written by RLE to Monsieur de Pastoret
      Includes: typescript copies of several letters
    - Manuscript copies of letters to Lady Romilly, 1814-23, and a description of one to Mrs. Kennedy, from Abbotsford (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - ALS to Miss Waring, Blacke-Castle- Roan, 1836 Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "On Reading Harrington," contemporary manuscript copy, in an unknown hand, of the letter and poem by Miss Phebe Yates of Liverpool which accompanied the Harrington portfolio to Miss Edgeworth, 1824 Oct 29
      Includes: typescript copies of letter
    - Contemporary manuscript copy, in an unknown hand, of Miss Edgeworth's letter to [Miss Phebe Yates] in appreciation of the gift of the Harrington Portfolio, 1824 Nov 24
      Includes: typescript copies of part of the letter
    - A detailed drawing in pencil of the designs on the cover of the Harrington portfolio, [n.p.], n.d.
      With a description, written in an unknown hand, and a typescript copy of the description
    - ALS to her publisher, Edgeworthstown, 1846 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Mentions her book, Early Lessons
    - Manuscript copies of other letters [to John Murray?], 1821-32, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - ANS to an unidentified recipient, Speenhamland, [England], [n.y.] Wed (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - WRITINGS AND DOCUMENTS BY AND ABOUT EDGEWORTH
    - Enigma, holograph poem by ME, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Fairholt, F. W. (Frederick William). Drawing of ME's library, with Miss Edgeworth at work there, n.d.
    - Photographs and postcards of Edgeworthstown, ME's library, and editions of her books (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Includes: Two copies of F. W. Fairholt's drawing, six postcards of Edgeworthstown and the library, a photograph of a copy of Orlandino, 1848, in illuminated paper boards, and a photograph of the spine of an early edition of Early Lessons
      Removed from Mrs. S. C. Hall's autograph album in 1931
  - COLLECTOR'S FILES
    - Correspondence
      - Arthur Rogers, bookseller, 1933-39, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Barnet B. Ruder, bookseller, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - [Barton?], Catherine, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Bernard Halliday, bookseller. Invoice and page of catalog description for Edgeworth material, 1938 Apr 20 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Bernard Quaritch, Ltd., 1932-34 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Birrell & Garnett, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Browne & Browne, 1933-34, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Butler, Harold Edgeworth, 1934-37, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - C. A. Stonehill, Jr. Page of catalog description of Edgeworth material, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Carnegie Book Shop, 1937 Feb 16 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Charles E. Tuttle Co., 1934, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1936-38 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Chas. J. Sawyer Ltd. Page of catalog description of Edgeworth material, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Crescent Cottage Bookshop, James Venn. Page of catalog description of Edgeworth material, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Dauber and Pine Bookshops, 1934 Jul 14 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Dobell's Antiquarian Bookstore, 1934-38 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Donnellan, M., 1935 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Dr. to D. Webster, bookseller. Invoice addressed to Catherine Barton, 1934 Dec 15 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Duttons, Inc., 1934-38 (Box 2, Folder 51-52)
      - Edgar H. Wells & Company, 1934-36, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Elkin Mathews, Limited, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - England, Sylvia, 1935-38 (Box 2, Folder 55)
        Includes: two letters from Sylvia England to Catherine Barton
      - English-Speaking Union, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - G.A. Baker & Co., 1936-37 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - George Bates, bookseller. Pages of catalog description of Edgeworth material, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - Goodspeed's Book Shop, 1936 Jun 11 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - Grolier Club, 1935, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - Henry Sotheran Ltd., 1936 Jun 12 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - Hodges, Figgis & Co., 1935 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - Hollings, Frank, 1936 Feb 12 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      - James F. Drake, Incorporated, 1934-35 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      - John Wiley & Sons, 1936 Jun 18 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      - Johnston, Henry, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - Macmann, M. J., 1935-36, n.d (Box 2, Folder 67)
      - Manly, M., 1935-36 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Maynadier, Gustavus Howard, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - Miley, Sara, [n.y.] Aug-Oct (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - Murray, John, 1935-36 (Box 2, Folder 71)
        Includes: one letter to from John Murray to Sylvia England
      - Newport Book Shop, 1934 May 21 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - Papantonio, Michael, 1936-40 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - Peabody Book Shop, 1934-35 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      - Peck, Frederick, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      - Pickering & Chatto Ltd., 1934-40 (Box 2, Folder 76-77)
      - Quinn, James H., 1935 Dec 12 (Box 2, Folder 78)
      - Sadleir, Michael, 1935-38 (Box 2, Folder 79-83)
      - Wormser, Richard S., 1936 Jun 29 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      - Other Correspondence, 1934-38 (Box 2, Folder 85-86)
    - Research Files
      - Works by Maria Edgeworth and Richard Lovell Edgeworth
        - Belinda (Box 3, Folder 87)
          Includes "Sheets of Signature I" of an edition published by J. Johnson
        - Belinda, transcription of a character sketch, entitled "Appendix" (Box 3, Folder 88)
        - The Bracelets, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 89)
        - Castle Rackrent, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 90)
        - Early Lessons, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 91)
        - Fashionable Tales, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 92)
        - Frank, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 93)
        - Garry Owen, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 94)
        - Harrington, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 95)
        - Harry and Lucy (Box 3, Folder 96)
        - Helen, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 97)
        - Memoirs of Richard Lovell Edgeworth, esq., 1936 May 8 (Box 3, Folder 98)
          TLS from Frederick G. Kilgour, of Harvard College Library, to Catherine Barton
        - The Modern Griselda, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 99)
        - Moral Tales, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 100)
        - The Parent's Assistant, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 101-102)
        - Poetry Explained for the Use of Young People by RLE, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103)
        - Popular Tales, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 104)
        - Professional Education by RLE, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 105)
        - A Rational Primer, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 106)
        - Readings on Poetry, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 107)
        - Rosamond (Box 3, Folder 108)
        - American Editions, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 109)
        - French Editions, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 110)
        - Late Editions, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 111)
      - Notes regarding Maria Edgeworth
        - Notecards regarding Edgeworth editions, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 112)
          Note on first card: "Edgeworth, British Museum. Mrs. Slade's cards"
        - Notes on ME's printers and publishers (Box 3, Folder 113)
        - Notes on ME's contributions to periodicals, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 114)
        - "Edgeworthiana," typescript bibliography of books and articles about ME (Box 3, Folder 115)
        - Lists of ME material in libraries, 1935-37, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 116-118)
        - Other notes and clippings, 1935-36, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 119)
      - Works by Bertha Coolidge Slade
        - Maria Edgeworth, a Bibliographical Tribute, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 120-122)
          Includes: Printed copies of several pages, prospectus lists, reviews, correspondence, and clippings
- Materials from Other Sources, 1799-1893, n.d.; Series II; 0.6; (2 boxes)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders
  - CORRESPONDENCE OF MARIA EDGEWORTH
    - 10 ALS to Mrs. Anna Letitia Barbauld, Edgeworthstown, 1799-1816 (Box 4, Folder 123-125)
      The letters of 1804 Sep 23, 1812 Sep 12, and 1816 Sep 3 also contain letters written and signed by RLE. The letter of 1812 Jun 28 is a copy made in 1858
    - 6 ALS from Mrs. Anna Letitia Barbauld, 1804, 1823 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - ALS to Sir Augustus Wall Callcott, [n.y.] Tue (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - ANS to Mrs. Coleman, Edgeworthstown, 1837 Sep 1 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - ALS to Lady Dacre, 1 North Audley St., [London], 1844 Mar 28 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - ALS to her brother, William Edgeworth, Edgeworth's Town, [Ireland], 1826 Dec 31 (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Note in third person to John Flaxman, Grove House, Kensington Gore, London, 1819 Mar 25 (Box 4, Folder 131)
      This is an inquiry about a bust of Dr. [Erasmus?] Darwin supposedly executed by Joseph Nollekens.
    - ALS to Mrs. Griffith, Edgeworthstown, 1823 Jan 13
    - ALS to Mrs. S. C. (Anna Maria Fielding) Hall, Brighton, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - ALS to Mr. Harness, 1841 Feb 23 (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - 2 ALS to Mary Holland, 1829 Apr 13, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 134)
      Includes: typescript copies
    - ALS to Mr. Hughes, Edgeworthstown, 1841 Jul 14 (Box 4, Folder 135)
    - ALS to Rowland Hunter, Edgeworthstown, 1827 Apr 2 (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - ALS to Camille Jordan, Edgeworthstown, 1821 Feb 3 (Box 4, Folder 137)
    - ALS to M. Julien, Edgeworthstown, 1827 Mar 20 (Box 4, Folder 138)
    - 2 ALS to Mr. and/or Mrs. F. T. Kennedy, Glasgow and Edgeworthstown, 1823 (Box 4, Folder 139)
    - ALS to Mr. Lees, Edgeworthstown, 1817 Jan 29 (Box 4, Folder 140)
      Note on verso of leaf 2 signed by R. W. Crewe, 1817 Feb 6
    - ALS to Mrs. Marshall, 1 North Audley Street, [n.y.] Tue (Box 4, Folder 141)
    - ALS to Lady Radstock, Kensington, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 142)
    - ALS to Gerald Ralston, Edgeworthstown, 1835 Jan 26 (Box 4, Folder 143)
    - 2 ALS to William Roscoe, Edgeworthstown, 1824, 1827 (Box 4, Folder 144)
      The letter of 1827 Apr 9 speaks of Captain Basil Hall
    - ALS to David Russell, Edgeworthstown, 1828 Dec 6 (Box 4, Folder 145)
      Sample of writing and autograph of Mrs. Elizabeth Hamilton pasted on verso of letter
    - ALS to Mrs. Sigourney, Edgeworthstown, 1846 Dec (Box 4, Folder 146)
    - ALS to Walter Sneyd, Edgeworthstown, 1820 Jan 9 (Box 4, Folder 147)
      On inside of envelope is an autographed drawing for her nephew
    - ALS to Mrs. Walter Sneyd, Edgeworthstown, 1819 Nov 4 (Box 4, Folder 148)
      Accompanied by a manuscript account of ME's life and work, in an unidentified hand, dated 1849 May 28
    - ALS to Miss Sneyd, Edgeworthstown, 1838 Apr 2 (Box 4, Folder 149)
    - ALS from R. Ward, Pall Mall, London, 1817 Feb 22 (Box 4, Folder 150)
    - MS copy of a letter to Thomas Winthrop, Edgeworthstown, 1835 Jan 25 (Box 4, Folder 151)
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Edgeworthstown, 1816 Jun 15 (Box 4, Folder 152)
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Edgeworthstown, 1824 Dec 21 (Box 4, Folder 153)
    - AL (in French) in third person to an unidentified recipient, Edgeworthstown, Ireland, 1829 Jun (Box 4, Folder 154)
    - Fragment of ANS to an unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 155)
    - Bound volume lettered on the spine, "Maria Edgeworth, 1767-1849", 1819-42, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 156)
      Contains letters to Mrs. Cropper, Mrs. Dillon, Mrs. Pakenham, and an unidentified recipient concerning Mrs. Carmichael's book, Tales of a Grandmother; ALS from Mrs. M. Ruxton to Miss Mills; a memorandum of a visit to Mr. and Mrs. [Samuel Carter?] Hall to Edgeworthstown; verse of six lines, probably in the hand of ME, with the initials "R. L. E. 1819"; a picture of ME and two clippings about her
  - LETTERS FROM RICHARD LOVELL EDGEWORTH
    - ALS to Mrs. Anna Letitia Barbauld, Edgeworthstown, 1804 Sep 4 (Box 4, Folder 157)
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Edgeworthstown, 1817 Jan 30 (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - WRITINGS AND DOCUMENTS BY AND ABOUT MARIA EDGEWORTH
    - Couplet, signed by ME, about Sir Walter Scott, 1826 Mar 28 (Box 4, Folder 159)
    - Collection of 18 engravings of Maria Edgeworth, n.d.
      Some signed by S. Hollyer, 1808-1897, New York and London. Accompanied by one engraving entitled, "View of Miss Edgeworth's Residence" by C. G. Childs
    - Raifford, Herbert. Pencil sketch of Maria Edgeworth's home in Edgeworthstown, signed and dated. Edgeworthstown House, Ireland, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 160)
    - Ewens, E. G. "Maria Edgeworth, A Study", [n.p.], typescript volume, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 161)
- Oversize, 1.25; (1 box)
  Oversize contains material from Series I and Series II, arranged in the order in which they appear in the series
  - ALS to Mrs. Miles (from Series I), 1815 Jan 17 (Box 6, Folder 162)
  - ALS to Madame de Pastoret with a postscript on an outside sheet (from Series I), 1814 Oct 10 (Box 6, Folder 163)
  - "On Reading Harrington" (from Series I), 1824 Oct 29 (Box 6, Folder 164)
  - Contemporary manuscript copy of Miss Edgeworth's letter to [Miss Phebe Yates] (from Series I), 1824 Nov 24 (Box 6, Folder 165)
  - A detailed drawing in pencil of the designs on the cover of the Harrington portfolio, [n.p.] (from Series I), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 166)
  - Fairholt, F. W. Drawing of Maria Edgeworth's library (from Series I), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 167)
  - 10 ALS to Mrs. Anna Letitia Barbauld, Edgeworthstown (from Series II), 1804, 1812 (Box 6, Folder 168)
  - 6 ALS from Mrs. Anna Letitia Barbauld (from Series II), 1804 Aug 30 (Box 6, Folder 169)
  - ALS to Mrs. Griffith, Edgeworthstown (from Series II), 1823 Jan 13 (Box 6, Folder 170)
  - Collection of 18 engravings of Maria Edgeworth (from Series II), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 171-172)